Okay ברכות Berachot 20, we pick up today on כ' עמוד ב'
chaf amud bet and we are at the two dots of אמר
רב אדא בר אהבה Amar Rav Adda bar Ahava נשים. Nashim. The
line starts with נשים, Nashim, it's about 20 lines down. So it
does seem the משנה Mishnah about the list of things women are
obligated and exempt from and the
גמרא Gemara referred to the basic דרשות drashot from which we know
this and what do and what doesn't fall into the rule of
positive time-bound מצוות, mitzvot, but the basic ones that we will focus
on for our interest is that
שמע Shema they're exempt because it's time-bound, שמונה עשרה Shmoneh Esrei תפילה
Tefillah they're obligated although in its rabbinic structured form it is time-bound
but at its core it is not time-bound prayer and ברכת המזון
Birkat Hamazon they are also obligated in because as well in its
core it is not a time-bound although our meals tend to be
at certain times the מצווה mitzvah is not time-bound. So now the
גמרא Gemara says like this. אמר רב אדא בר אהבה נשים חייבות
בקידוש היום דאורייתא. Amar Rav Adda bar Ahava Nashim chayavot bekiddush hayom
d'oraita.
Now here we get to a very important גמרא Gemara parallel with
other גמרות Gemaras about women's obligation in other matters whether it's biblical
or rabbinic whether it does and even if it doesn't necessarily follow
the time-bound rule. Women are obligated making קידוש Kiddush on שבת Shabbat
biblically. Okay, now our form of קידוש Kiddush is over a cup
of wine and declaring מקדש השבת mekadesh hashabbat and declaring that the
day is
שבת. Shabbat. Most assume that the wine is only מדרבנן miderabbanan but
at least there is a biblical מצווה mitzvah of זכור את יום
השבת לקדשו Zachor et yom hashabbat lekadesho to make קידוש Kiddush on
שבת Shabbat to declare the sanctity of שבת. Shabbat. So he says
that's biblical. אמאי? Amai? Why is that? מצוות עשה שהזמן גרמא הוא
וכל מצוות עשה שהזמן גרמא נשים פטורות. Mitzvat aseh shehazman grama hu
vechol mitzvat aseh shehazman grama nashim pturot. Every time-bound if it's time-bound
and every time-bound מצווה mitzvah women are exempt. Again, although the rule
is often violated. So here will be another violation of that rule.
אמר אביי מדרבנן. Amar Abaye miderabbanan. Fine, we only know it rabbinically.
אמר ליה רבא, Amlei Rava, Rava said to אביי, Abaye, והא דאורייתא
קאמר, ve-ha d'oraita ka'amar, biblically they're obligated. ועוד כל מצוות עשה נחייבינהו
מדרבנן? Ve'od kol mitzvat aseh nikhayeivinhu miderabbanan?
And if you say that the rabbis obligated them on these מצוות
mitzvot they're exempt from, these non-time-bound מצוות, mitzvot, then we should be
consistent. We should obligate them for every non-time-bound מצווה mitzvah and we
know that's not true. So obviously there has to be something unique
about קידוש. Kiddush. Even if you want to claim it's rabbinic, you
can't just say מדרבנן. miderabbanan. Why this more than other things? And
anyway we're not even saying rabbinically we're saying biblically. So what is
unique about קידוש? Kiddush? אלא אמר רבא אמר קרא, Ela amar Rava
amar kra, here's what we're saying. The verse says זכור ושמור. Zachor
ve-Shamor.
Remember the שבת Shabbat to keep it holy and observe it to
keep it holy. כל שישנו בשמירה ישנו בזכירה: Kol she-yeshno bi-shmirah yeshno
bi-zkirah: anybody that's commanded in observing, protecting, which means to not violate
the שבת, Shabbat, not to do a מלאכה, melacha, has the linked
obligation of remembering, of making קידוש, Kiddush, of declaring its sanctity. והני
נשים הואיל ואיתנהו בשמירה איתנהו בזכירה: Ve-hanei nashim ho'il ve-itnehu bi-shmirah itnehu
bi-zkirah: when it comes to women, since they are bound to observe
שבת, Shabbat, they're also bound to remember שבת. Shabbat. And from there
we actually rule that women are obligated in קידוש Kiddush דאורייתא d'oraita
which raises the issue about women being מוציא motzi men in קידוש
Kiddush which for any of those who have any issues with it
they only have very secondary issues about whether it's appropriate, זילא מילתא,
zila milta, those types of issues but everybody does agree at the
core that men and women have an equal obligation of קידוש Kiddush
and women can be מוציא motzi men. Another interesting question which we're
not going to discuss, I know last time I said something and
everybody wanted to know the answer but I'll just put here as
a footnote, is about הבדלה Havdalah because הבדלה Havdalah often is understood
by many to be biblical as well linked to זכירה. zkirah. You
remember שבת Shabbat when it begins then when it ends you declare
its boundaries as it were to begin and at the end. And
therefore women's obligation in הבדלה Havdalah same as men's and a woman
could make הבדלה Havdalah for a man or certainly be מוציא motzi
herself. It becomes an interesting discussion how according to some ראשונים Rishonim
and פוסקים, Poskim, A, women's obligation is different than men's in הבדלה
Havdalah and they can't be מוציא motzi a man, it's מדרבנן, miderabbanan,
but B, a very strange and unusual idea that a woman can't
even be מוציא motzi make הבדלה Havdalah for herself. She has to
hear it from a man, which is very strange. When did we
ever hear of anything like that, that you're exempt or you're not
obligated enough but to even do something for yourself? So that is
a whole discussion but again the simple position
of the סוגיות sugyot and of most of the פוסקים Poskim is
that women by הבדלה Havdalah as well are equally obligated as men
and certainly at minimum we should be able to do it for
themselves. Yes.
Well, we do have one whole section of הלכה, Halakha, fine, might
be obligated in קרבן מוסף Korban Musaf בעבודה be-avodah cannot be done
by the...
Yes, okay, fine.
But does that indicate anything else?
Right. Yes.
So, you know, I've heard this דרשה drasha a thousand times but
just now thinking about it, but what kind of דרשה drasha is
this? In other words, it's not like what's the basis of this
דרשה? drasha? Is it a היקש? hekesh? Because it's not a קל
וחומר, kal v'chomer, it's not a... Yeah, but I don't know if
it's a גזירה שווה.
gzeira shava. It's something like that. לוחות ראשונות Luchot rishonot and לוחות
שניות luchot shniyot and זכור ושמור בדיבור אחד נאמרו. Zachor ve-Shamor b'dibbur
echad ne'emru. So to assume that those two concepts are intrinsically linked.
So it's basically like a גזירה שווה gzeira shava with the same
words.
Not something like that, yes. It's not a גזירה שווה gzeira shava
like literally the same words. Yes. It's true, I mean, using the
לוחות ראשונות luchos rishonos and שניות shnios and the parallels there, it's
distinctive for the לוחות, luchos, yes.
What about other lists of people than women like slaves or...
So slaves, yes, slaves' obligation follows women's obligations. So slaves would be
the same. Minors, minors would always be not because minors always are
not yet of age, so they're always rabbinic. What about why slaves
aren't included in a מנין? minyan?
Who else are you referring to?
I don't know. In terms of the... yes. Anyway, the normal world
we divide it into here where it's men, women, slaves, and minors.
But the people that are not בר דעת bar daas like minors,
like the חרש שוטה וקטן cheresh shoteh v'katan and so on, but
those also, those are always exempt because minor חרש שוטה וקטן cheresh
shoteh v'katan is one category of exemption which has to do with
not yet being considered, you know, an adult or of right mind,
and those are always exempt. I mean, there's a here and there,
sometimes a קטן katan is excluded for certain reasons. And then the
in terms of the world of people that are of mature, right
mind, adults and so on, the world is divided between, you know,
men, women, and slaves. And so what women are obligated, slaves are
obligated as well.
And then the poll about women doing Havdalah.
I knew that was going to be the question. Depends who you
ask, okay?
If you want to know, you can ask me afterwards. All right,
so now what I think, all right, so now the גמרא Gemara
says like this: אמר ליה רבינא לרבא. Amar leh Ravina l'Rava. Okay,
לרבות. lerabbos. So now that we're talking about women's obligation and the
משנה Mishnah mentioned ברכת המזון Birchas Hamazon that women are obligated, now
we're going to have an interesting raise some questions about that. So
אמר ליה רבינא לרבא. Amar leh Ravina l'Rava. So Ravina says to
Rava: נשים בברכת המזון דאורייתא או דרבנן? Nashim b'Birchas Hamazon d'Oraisa o
d'Rabbanan?
Women in benching, is it biblical or rabbinic? Okay, the difference would
be like if a woman could be מוציא motzi a man, although
that raises other questions about זימון zimum which we'll get to. But
let's even bracket if she could be מוציא motzi somebody else and
because again that has to do something with the structure of זימון,
zimum, but anyway is it biblical or rabbinic? למאי נפקא מינה? L'mai
nafka mina? לאפוקי רבים ידי חובתן. L'afokei rabbim yedei chovasan. So there
we go, right? I just bracketed it but it was in brackets.
Okay, to be מוציא, motzi, I forgot the next line, to be
מוציא motzi others their obligation. אי אמרת דאורייתא, Ei amrat d'Oraisa,
if it's biblical, אתי דאורייתא ומפקי דאורייתא, ati d'Oraisa u'mafkei d'Oraisa, then
a woman could be מוציא motzi a man, a דאורייתא d'Oraisa could
be מוציא motzi a דאורייתא. d'Oraisa.
אי אמרת דרבנן, Ei amrat d'Rabbanan, if it's rabbinic, הוי שאינו מחויב
בדבר, havi she'eino mechuyav b'davar, they're not obligated, וכל שאינו מחויב בדבר
אינו מוציא את הרבים ידי חובתן. v'chol she'eino mechuyav b'davar eino motzi
es harabbim yedei chovasan. If they're not obligated, they cannot מוציא motzi
other people, they cannot discharge other people of their obligation. So as
I
sort of said by bracketing it, we'll see when we get to
later פרקים perakim and we discuss ברכת המזון Birchas Hamazon and we
discuss the institution of זימון, zimum, you know, that there's other considerations
as well. But at least at its core, before we get to
questions about זימון, zimum, let's ask if they have equal obligation to
men and can they in principle מוציא motzi men or not? מאי?
Mai? What's the story? תא שמע, Ta shma, come and hear, ואמת
אמרו, v'emes amru, they in truth they said, this is from סוכה,
Sukkah, a תוספתא, Tosefta, בן מברך לאביו, bein mevarech l'aviv, ועבד מברך
לרבו, ve'eved mevarech l'rabbo, ואשה מברכת לבעלה. v'ishah mevareches l'baalah.
A son can do ברכת המזון Birchas Hamazon for his father, a
slave for his master, a woman for her husband. אבל אמרו חכמים,
Aval amru chachamim, even though in principle that's true, the rabbis said,
תבא מארה לאדם שאשה ובניו מברכין לו. tavo me'eirah l'adam she'ishah u'vanav
mevarchin lo. A curse should be upon a person that whose wife
and son have to have to bench for him, have to do
ברכת המזון Birchas Hamazon for him, because presumably that would only be
that would reflect the fact that he was ignorant and not able
to do it himself. This was all right, this was in a
what
what if he were ill?
Oh, ill, okay. But this is assuming not those special cases
of מארה me'eirah on the woman who needs her husband to bench.
Right,
so obviously we're not saying that. This is in a cultural context
where the this is in a cultural context where egalitarianism was not
a value. B, the no kidding, B, the assumption generally speaking, generally
speaking, men were literate and women were not. So in that type
of a context, if a woman is reading for her husband, it
basically could be of no other reason other than that the woman
is literate and the man isn't, which in that context cultural context
is a shame and an embarrassment for the man. So that's what
yes.
Is that when you talk about literacy, it was my understanding in
antiquity
that very few people were literate.
The only thing that was actually read was say the שמע Shema
from the scroll of the Torah when they said קריאת שמע, Krias
Shema, they read it. All of this, including משנה, Mishnah, everything was
בעל פה. ba'al peh. So what's the הוא אמינא hava amina that
the women couldn't memorize the words of ברכת המזון?
Birchas Hamazon? It's an interesting question, you know, rhythm, I don't know,
or maybe they right, so it's not just about literate, it was
really about how well-schooled they were in general and everything else.
Every three-year-old can memorize ברכת המזון. Birchas Hamazon.
Although I will tell you that the reason why nowadays, I have
to tell you this, the reason why nowadays every three-year-old knows ברכת
המזון Birchas Hamazon and it's known, you know, like across you know
denominations even, is because yeah you know about that? is because of
the music. Because we have this
music for ברכת המזון Birchas Hamazon that every... easy for everybody to
memorize, and this, the music that everybody sings was the contest winner.
Unbelievable! And so imagine what this person did for כל ישראל Klal
Yisrael with this music for ברכת המזון. Birkat Hamazon. Right? Okay, but
anyway, but your point is still well taken: how hard is it
to know ברכת המזון? Birkat Hamazon?
Again, yeah, it went to some level of chanting with the music.
Alright, so I got it. I don't know the full answer, but
it is clear though, I think we can accept even if women
knew it as much as men, because it was certainly talking in
a context in which,
you know, it would be
egalitarianism was not a value. There was a sense about sort of,
you know, the patriarchy and emphasizing the fact that the man is
the head of the household, so to be dependent on his wife
for whatever reason. Why is he dependent on his wife? Why doesn't
the man know it? Clearly, there were people that did not know
it, that were not even literate enough, you know, or well-schooled enough
to know it. So that is the context in which we say,
in which this is making its statement. One minute, let's just finish
the point. Okay. So that's what this ברייתא braita says, that's what
this תוספתא tosefta says. That in principle, yes, but it's an embarrassment.
So אי אמרת, ei amarta, so let's take a look. אי אמרת
בשלמא דאורייתא, ei amarta bishlama de'oraita, if you say it's biblical, אתי
דאורייתא ומפיק דאורייתא, ati de'oraita umapik de'oraita, I understand why in principle
the woman could be מוציא motzi her, the wife could be מוציא
motzi her husband, forget the מארה, me'era, the curse, because they're same
obligation. אלא אי אמרת דרבנן, ela ei amarta derabbanan, if it's rabbinic,
אתי דרבנן ומפיק דאורייתא? ati derabbanan umapik de'oraita? Can a rabbinic obligation
for, you know, discharge a biblical one? So the גמרא Gemara says
that proves it's biblical. So the גמרא Gemara says you prove too
much. ולטעמיך, u'letamecha, according to your reasoning, קטן בר חיובא הוא? katan
bar chiyuva hu? It says that a minor also can be, discharge
his father his obligation. So a minor isn't obligated biblically, so how
do you explain that the minor can do it for the father?
Clearly, they're not at the same level of obligation. So that's not
what's going on here. אלא הכא במאי עסקינן, ela hacha bemai askinan,
what are we talking about? כגון שאכל שיעור דרבנן, kegon she'achal shiur
derabbanan, דאתי דרבנן ומפיק דרבנן. de'ati derabbanan umapik derabbanan. We're talking about
a special case, that the father ate not an amount that obligated
biblically. The תורה Torah says ואכלת ושבעת וברכת, ve'achalta vesavata uverachta, you'll
eat and be sated. So biblically your obligation to do ברכת המזון
Birkat Hamazon is only when there is you're really sated, you've eaten
enough food to really fill you. Rabbinically you're obligated even if you
just eat like a כזית kezayit or maybe a כביצה, kebeitzah, which
we'll talk about in a minute. So therefore, if you eat a
small amount, you could be obligated rabbinically and not biblically. So the
גמרא Gemara has an interesting mix and match here. You are an
adult male, you're obligated biblically, but you ate an amount that only
obligates you rabbinically, you only ate a כזית. kezayit. This person here,
this minor, is only rabbinically obligated. Maybe he ate a full meal,
but he's only rabbinically obligated. So since this is a rabbinic obligation
and this is a rabbinic, although one is a person at the
biblical level but the particular context, the amount they ate is only
a rabbinic amount, this rabbinic can discharge that rabbinic for at the
same level. This leads to whole discussions in ראשונים Rishonim about can
what if you're a double דרבנן, derabbanan, can that be מוציא motzi
one דרבנן? derabbanan? Like can a minor, let's say by מגילה, Megillah,
right, both of them can a minor be מוציא motzi an adult
by מגילה? Megillah? Well, it's all rabbinic. Yes, but for the adult,
he's of the right age, it's only as it were one דרבנן.
derabbanan. The minor is below the age, so it's a דרבנן derabbanan
of a דרבנן. derabbanan. Gets to whole levels of discussions. The other
interesting thing to think about which the גמרא Gemara is not saying
here, as this was in the context of saying the הלל, Hallel,
and it could actually be that it's not an issue of discharging
for somebody else. It didn't say מוציא את אביו, motzi et aviv,
which means you discharge, it says מברך, mevarech, and one could imagine
that the son reads and the father repeats, or the wife reads
and the husband repeats. So you're not actually discharging, you are just
having me read along with you and helping me do it. Anyway,
the גמרא Gemara one way or the other says this is not
relevant and therefore we don't know the answer to whether women's obligation
is biblical or not. Now the question is, why would it not
be biblical? Right, the משנה Mishnah says women are obligated by ברכת
המזון. Birkat Hamazon. We said it's not time-bound, why would it not
be biblical? So רש"י Rashi says it is not biblical but, so
רש"י Rashi says, if you look at רש"י, Rashi,
רש"י Rashi says דרבנן דכתיב על הארץ הטובה אשר נתן לך והארץ
לא ניתנה לנקבה להתחלק. derabbanan dechtiv al ha’aretz hatovah asher natan lach
veha’aretz lo nitna lenekeva lehitchalek. That part of the ברכת המזון, Birkat
Hamazon, now this is something that we tend to lose sight of,
right, when we make ברכת המזון, Birkat Hamazon, since we are certainly
making them in חוץ לארץ, chut l'aretz, almost always but whatever, for
most people here, you know we focus on the ברכה bracha הזן
את הכל. hazan et hakol. It's about giving us the food, right,
ברכת המזון. Birkat Hamazon. But in the פסוקים, psukim, it's you go,
you're going to go into this land, the land of Israel, benefit
from all its goodness, ואכלת ושבעת ve'achalta vesavata of the land, וברכת
את ה' אלוהיך על הארץ uverachta et Hashem Elohecha al ha'aretz הטובה
אשר נתן לך. hatovah asher natan lach. Thank God for the land.
The eating of the food makes us appreciate the land of Israel
that God has given us, which is the ברכה bracha of על
הארץ ועל המזון, al ha'aretz ve'al hamazon, the second ברכה. bracha. And
that is a biblical part
of the
ברכת המזון. Birkat Hamazon. the eating of food wherever you're eating it
has to connect back to an appreciation of the land that God
has given us, that, you know, that even if we're not in
right now, but ultimately is the land in which we will reap
these benefits. So the, so he suggests that the reason women would
be exempt is because they never are direct inheritors of the land.
They might get it indirectly if, you know, there're no sons in
the family, but they're never direct inheritors of the land. תוספות Tosafot
rejects this. תוספות Tosafot says if that's true, you should ask about
כהנים Kohanim and לויים Levi'im as well and other people who don't
get the land, גרים. Geirim. There are people.
But what about the two sisters who got? Yeah, but that's not
direct. That's only if there are no sons. It's never sort of
on your own. It's never as the primary, it's never as the
primary recipient. Anyway, so תוספות Tosafot says if that were true, we
should have a discussion about all of others. So that's not the
issue. Collectively as a people, we receive the land, and that's not
an issue. So what does תוספות Tosafot say the issue is? So
תוספות Tosafot says the issue is something that even less central to
the biblical מצווה. mitzvah. He quotes a גמרא Gemara later that says
if you don't say ברית bris and תורה, Torah, על בריתך שחתמת
בבשרנו al brischa shechatamta bivsareinu ועל תורתך שלימדתנו, v'al torascha shelimaditanu, that
you're not יצא. yotzei. So he takes that גמרא Gemara literally to
mean you're not even biblically יצא. yotzei. And I don't know, but
the גמרא's Gemara trying to explain this גמרא, Gemara, and therefore that's
תוספות's Tosafot explanation that maybe women who don't have a ברית מילה,
bris milah, if you understand ברית bris in the very, you know,
literal sense or whatever, על בריתך שחתמת בבשרנו, al brischa shechatamta bivsareinu,
and who are not obligated in תלמוד תורה Talmud Torah as we
said before, that might exempt them. Of course, that's harder to understand
why that should matter biblically because neither of those themes are all
indicated in the תורה, Torah, and in general it's a question, right,
why is that a part of the ברכת המזון? birkat hamazon? So
רש''י Rashi and תוספות Tosafot have these different explanations, but it's hard
to understand what the גמרא's Gemara הוה אמינה hava amina is, and
you know, and although the what is the conclusion of the גמרא
Gemara does remain to a certain degree open, but given that the
הוה אמינה hava amina is a little unclear and the simple sense
of the משנה Mishnah is women are obligated, certainly the פשט pshat
is that women's obligation for ברכת המזון birkat hamazon is the same
as men's. How this relates to זימון zimmun is a different question
because זימון zimmun is a different institution. That's what I was alluding
to before. It's one thing if it's just me and you together,
no זימון. zimmun. I'm saying it, you're listening, maybe you can be
יצא yotzei or not based on the normal idea that I could
be מוציא motzi you. Maybe not, there's other considerations as well. But
זימון, zimmun, the way זימון zimmun originally existed was that, you know,
well, you know what, let's just leave it at that for now.
Okay, we'll talk about זימון zimmun more when we get to it.
Anyway, so here the גמרא Gemara says that this is that this
is the question about whether women are obligated equal to men, can
they be מוציא motzi men, and it's doing it, I'll just say
for now, outside of the זימון zimmun context and it leaves the
answer undetermined. Let's see till the end now of the משנה, Mishnah,
since I mentioned we mentioned this issue about the rabbinic level of
obligation. דרש רב אבירא, darash Rav Avira,
so רב אבירא Rav Avira made the following דרשה. drasha. זימנין אמר
ליה משמיה דרב אמי וזימנין אמר ליה משמיה דרב אסי. zimnin amar
lei mishmei d'Rav Ammi v'zimnin amar lei mishmei d'Rav Assi. Sometimes in
the name of רב אמי, Rav Ammi, sometimes name of רב אסי.
Rav Assi. אמרו מלאכי השרת לפני הקדוש ברוך הוא. amru malachei hasharei
lifnei Hakadosh Baruch Hu. The angels, heavenly angels said to God, ריבונו
של עולם, Ribbono shel olam, Master of the Universe, כתוב בתורתך, kasuv
b'torascha,
it says in Your תורה, Torah, אשר לא ישא פנים ולא יקח
שוחד, asher lo yissa panim v'lo yikach shochad,
God does not show favor or take bribes. והלא, v'halo, right, this
is פרשת לא תקח שוחד parshas lo tikach shochad for us. והלא
אתה נושא פנים לישראל, v'halo ata nosei panim l'Yisrael, but You show
favor to Israel. דכתיב ישא ה' פניו אליך, d'kasiv yissa Hashem panav
eilecha, God will lift up His countenance to you. Now תוספות Tosafot
points out that's not פשט, pshat, it doesn't mean that He's going
to favor us over others, right, it just means that He shows
favor towards us. But anyway, nevertheless he says you show favor to
Israel, how can this be?
So the גמרא Gemara says, וכי לא אשא פנים לישראל, v'chi lo
essa panim l'Yisrael, shall I not show favor to Israel, שכתבתי להם
בתורה, shekasavti lahem b'Torah, I said I wrote for them in the
תורה, Torah, ואכלת ושבעת וברכת את ה' אלוהיך, v'achalta v'savata u'veirachta es
Hashem Elohecha, that they only have to do ברכת המזון birkat hamazon
after they're sated. והם מדקדקין על עצמן עד כזית ועד כביצה, ve'hem
medakdekin al atzman ad k'zayit v'ad k'beitzah, and they are so careful
that even if it's as little as a כזית, ke'zayit, an olive,
or an egg amount, כביצה, ke'beitzah, they obligate themselves rabbinically in the
מצווה. mitzvah. So since they do more than is demanded of them,
I will act towards them in a way that is more than
is, you know, the שורת הדין, shurat hadin, the that is the
sort of the strict justice because they are doing more, I will
do more as well. Okay, now the גמרא, Gemara,
so now we go on, so that was a nice ending of
the benching. Now we make a quick abrupt shift from the questions
of who's obligated to certain people that might not be able to
say the
קריאת שמע. Keriyat Shema. Let's take a look. בעל קרי מהרהר בלבו
ואינו מברך לא לפניו ולא לאחריו. ba'al keri meharher belibo v'eino mevarech
lo lefanav v'lo leacharav. A person who is a בעל קרי, ba'al
keri, literally means somebody who is a person of a nocturnal emission,
a man who has had a seminal emission, who has a טומאה
tumah until he actually goes to the מקווה. mikvah.
And then by the nightfall he's completely טהור, tahor, after the מקווה
mikvah he's mostly טהור. tahor. So he, the assumption here is that
there's a problem with him davening and saying the שמע Shema and
saying שמונה עשרה. Shemoneh Esrei. So what does he do? מהרהר בלבו
ואינו מברך לא לפניו ולא לאחריו. meharher belibo v'eino mevarech lo lefanav
v'lo leacharav. He thinks the שמע. Shema. In his heart, but he
does not make the ברכות brachos before or after. The basic rule
being he does the biblical, not the rabbinic. So the שמע, Shema,
the core שמע Shema is biblical, he does that, he thinks that,
but he doesn't make the ברכות, brachos, that's only rabbinic.
I'm sorry, is this before or after he goes to the מקווה?
mikvah?
Let's hold off for that right now, let's just assume before for
okay for now we'll assume before going to the מקווה. mikvah.
Even with the שמע Shema you have to listen to it with
your ears.
Yeah, okay. And we'll talk about. ועל המזון מברך לאחריו ואינו מברך
לפניו. Ve'al hamazon mevarech leacharav ve'eino mevarech lefanav. Now for בענטשינג, benching,
which the בענטשינג benching afterwards is biblical as we've been saying, beforehand
the ברכת המזון Birkat Hamazone in the sense of over the food,
the ברכת הנהנין, birchas hanehenin, the ברכה bracha on bread and on
food is rabbinic. So therefore you make the ברכת המזון Birkat Hamazone
at the end which is biblical, and he does not make the
ברכת המזון Birkat Hamazone in the beginning. So he does what's biblical,
not what's rabbinic. רבי יהודה אומר מברך לפניו ולאחריו. Rabbi Yehuda omer
mevarech lefanav uleacharav. Rabbi Yehuda says no, you can make the ברכות
brachos before and after, I'm not concerned with the fact that this
person is a בעל קרי. ba'al keri. Now as I said we'll
worry about Rabbi Yehuda in a minute, but the basic rule here
is do the biblical, don't do the rabbinic. We haven't yet understood
why can't he do, why is he at all limited? We'll get
to that.
But even before we get to that, I want to point out
another lack of symmetry here, which is the thing that he is
doing, how is he doing it? The שמע Shema that he's doing,
he's doing just by thinking. The תפילה tefilla that he's doing, the
ברכת המזון Birkat Hamazone that he's doing, he's actually enunciating. Why is
there that difference? So there are some ראשונים, rishonim, the תלמידי רבינו
יונה, talmidei Rabbeinu Yona, who say that even when he says it
says he does the ברכת המזון Birkat Hamazone it just means he
thinks it. It doesn't mean that he says it. Okay, I know,
but that's what he says. Now another possibility though is that the
שמע, Shema, if you remember, there is a strong emphasis on כוונה.
kavana. אחרי כוונת הלב הם הם הדברים, Acharei kavanat halev hem hem
hadvarim, right, there's a strong emphasis on שמע Shema on about thinking
about what it means. And there was even an opinion earlier that
it was just מצות כוונה, mitzvat kavana, not מצות קריאה. mitzvat kriya.
So normally we understand כוונה kavana as an additional criteria, you have
to be thinking about מלכות שמים. malchut shamayim. But it could be
the emphasis is so heavy that therefore maybe you fulfill the obligation
without even enunciating, and maybe that's more true by שמע Shema than
it is by ברכת המזון Birkat Hamazone because of that emphasis of
שמע Shema on the, you know, על לבבך al levavecha on the
כוונה. kavana. We'll continue, well we'll give another explanation in a minute
but for now we should note that even what you are doing,
there's an asymmetry between the שמע Shema and the ברכת המזון. Birkat
Hamazone. Yeah?
Does this confuse over one thing because the end of the גמרא
Gemara leading up to this משנה Mishnah was saying they were מדקדק
medakdek to even do it on a כביצה k'beitza or a כזית.
k'zayit. So are we saying that if we do that and we're
not full what's really not full in that? Is that still a
biblical obligation
to בענטש bench on less than a כזית k'zayit and less than
a כביצה? k'beitza?
What, what? No, no, no. כזית k'zayit and כביצה k'beitza is rabbinic
and only until you're full and only when you're full is it
biblical.
Right, so that means our if we're not full our ברכת המזון
Birkat Hamazone would only be rabbinic. Right, so
I
guess we're talking about in this case with the בעל קרי ba'al
keri who מברך לאחריו mevarech leacharav yeah, yeah, yeah.
So what we're talking about these as דאורייתא d'oraita we're assuming yes,
we're assuming that it has the amount that is דאורייתא, d'oraita, that
is correct. Rabbi?
Yes. You don't think that the issue with בעל קרי ba'al keri
and קריאת שמע k'riat Shma again has to do with the use
of the ספר תורה sefer Torah or the קלף klaf for actually
reading the שמע? Shema?
And you think that's why you can't enunciate by the שמע Shema
because of the words of the תורה Torah are more directly words
of תורה Torah than, so that's a very interesting point, right,
by reading it from the קלף.
klaf. Okay, that's an interesting point that if maybe the reason that
even by the שמע Shema what we're allowing you to do we
don't let you do it out loud because you're directly sort of
reading the words of תורה Torah that's even more of a problem
for a בעל קרי. ba'al keri. So rather than the approach I
was doing which is that there's a way you could be יוצא
yotzei שמע Shema with a lower threshold than יוצא yotzei ברכת המזון,
Birkat Hamazone, you're saying that there's a higher problem of enunciating whereas
by ברכת המזון Birkat Hamazone we can more allow it when it's
strictly necessary. That's an interesting point. Thank you. It's a good point.
So let's take a look what the גמרא Gemara says. אמר רבינא
זאת אומרת, Amar Ravina zot omeret, so now we're trying to focus
on why this why does thinking the שמע Shema help? So says
רבינא Ravina or what's the point of thinking it rather than saying
it? זאת אומרת, zot omeret, this tells you הרהור כדיבור דמי, hirhur
kedibbur dami, that thinking is like speaking it. דאי סלקא דעתך לאו
כדיבור דמי, de'i salka da'atach la'av kedibbur dami, if thinking did not
count as speaking, למה מהרהר, lama meharher, why bother thinking it? So
you know if you're saying think the שמע Shema it's gotta work,
it's gotta work, so thinking counts as if you said it. אלא
מה, Ella mah, so גמרא Gemara says one minute, so what do
you want to say? הרהור כדיבור דמי, hirhur kedibbur dami, thinking is
like you said it? So then if it's like you said it,
יוציא בשפתיו, yotzi bisiftav, might as well just say it. So the
גמרא Gemara answers כדאתן בסיני. kede'at-han beSinai. No, it's like הר סיני.
Har Sinai. What does that mean? It means what we're going to
find out is that the reason that a בעל קרי ba'al keri
does not say שמע Shema or תפילה tefilla or ברכת המזון Birkat
Hamazone is because of הר סיני, Har Sinai, right they're told you
know the men are told don't be with women for three days,
אל תגשו אל אשה, al tigshu el isha, which presumably means that
they cannot have just had sex and have been, or the גמרא
Gemara interprets it more not just about sex although I'll tell you
in a minute, but to have had seminal emission and be there
receiving the תורה, Torah, one of the reasons the גמרא Gemara interprets
it that way is not just about sex although partly because you
know the טומאה tuma is about the seminal emission but... But also
because the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* says that the women, the reason for
the three days, well if it was a man just do one
day, not having had sex, the reason for the three days was
because the women and the, interestingly, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, the פסוקים
Pesukim *Pesukim* emphasize the men. You're going to receive the תורה Torah
*Torah* don't be with a woman, talking about to the men. But
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, oh, the reason for the three days
is because if the women have had sex with their husbands within
the last three days, then their then semen might still be coming
out of their bodies. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* actually brings the
women back into the picture and makes it not about the having
the sex, but about the semen coming out of the body even
for women. And therefore according to the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, that is
a type of a state in which it's not appropriate to receive
the תורה Torah, *Torah*. Not just about... it's about being טמא *tamei*.
We'll see this later in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. You could have
touched a corpse and be much more טמא *tamei* than have had
a seminal emission. But it's about a type of a frame of
mind, again, not saying that sex is bad, but it's a very
type of a very sort of
physical expression of the body which is not the state of mind
to be in when one is receiving or right in the aftermath
of when one is receiving the תורה Torah, *Torah*. And that's the
concerns around sort of the בעל קרי baal keri *ba'al keri* and
seminal emission and then sort of being, saying the שמע Shema *Shema*
and doing these types of activities. So the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* says,
okay, but that case, God's word was explicit, was enunciated, it wasn't
just thought. You're actually dealing with the direct word of God. So
we're not going to say you can't think תורה Torah *Torah*, we're
going to say you can't like be speaking תורה Torah, *Torah* and
enunciating and have that spoken word, but just to think is not
a problem. And תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* of course points out, they weren't
speaking at הר סיני *Har Sinai*, they were just listening, but you
still had that spoken word of... the spoken word that was being
addressed, it wasn't just nobody saying anything, it's just going on in
my head. You actually had the word out there, which ties in
a little to maybe what Dov was saying, that maybe it's even
more of a problem when the word is actually the written word
and it's coming from a קלף *klaf* and it's direct תורה Torah
*Torah* words rather than a
Rabbinic text or ברכת המזון Birkat HaMazon *Birkat Hamazon*.
It's also interesting that he use... the parallel is the human being
enunciating the words of the שמע Shema *Shema* is a microcosmic parallel
to God saying the עשרת הדברות *Aseret Hadiberot*.
Right. And that is... thank you, and that is an excellent point
and that is exactly it, that if you, I think even רש"י
Rashi *Rashi* says, let me just check רש"י Rashi *Rashi*. Well, right,
רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says in general, ודברת בם *Vedibarta Bam* לבניך *levanecha*,
the פסוק Pasuk *pasuk* later that the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is going
to quote, ודברת בם *Vedibarta Bam*, you shall teach your children, יום
אשר עמדת לפני ה' אלהיך בחורב *Yom Asher Amadeta Lifnei Hashem Elokecha
Bechorev*, when you stood before God, but the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* actually
says that every learning of תורה Torah *Torah* can be seen as
a microcosm, as a reenactment of מעמד הר סיני *Ma'amad Har Sinai*,
every learning of תורה Torah, *Torah* and yes, certainly the שמע Shema
*Shema*. And therefore, that is the issue about being a בעל קרי
baal keri *ba'al keri*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s answer is, you're
יוצא yotzei *yotzei*, you're יוצא yotzei *yotzei* by thinking, but in terms
of the idea of this direct encountering of the word of God,
that is not such a problem if you don't actually say it.
Yes, Rachel.
But is בעל קרי baal keri, *ba'al keri* in תנ"ך *Tanakh*?
So,
he is טמא *tamei*, but that's not the relevant point.
That's not the relevant point.
The relevant point is that he had a seminal emission and
he can't say שמע Shema.
*Shema*. Yes, absolutely. It's all about קרי *keri*. It's all about the
seminal emission.
Is it a seminal emission
over the night or because of sexual relations?
Either way. Either way. Right. Even if he was doing a מצוה
mitzvah *mitzvah*, you know, even if he was having sex with his
wife and they were, they were having... you know, they were doing...
being עוסק במצוה פרו ורבו *osek b'mitzvah p'ru u'rvu*. It's not about
doing something wrong. It's about the sort of... very physical... it's like
ויחזו את האלהים ויאכלו וישתו *Vayechezu et Ha'elohim Vayochlu Vayishtu*, right? It's
like here you are seeing God and
you're busy eating while you're... while you're having a vision of God.
It's just too... there's nothing wrong with eating, but it's not what
you... it's... it's too much of that
physical expression of who we are that... that... which should not be
sort of being intertwined with this very spiritual experience. But we say
שמע Shema *Shema* every day.
Yes. So that's why we have him say it בהרהור *behirhur*. We
find a way to say it, okay, but not in a way
that's going to skirt this problem. Yes, Rachel.
Didn't he go both ways? Didn't he say the... so he means
that you don't need to hear it. Right, so he answers... over
saying even according to the one who says you do have to
hear it, making an exception. Well, let's take a look. So the
גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* asks... that's one opinion, okay. One opinion is you're
יוצא yotzei *yotzei*, but the specific problem about being a בעל קרי
baal keri *ba'al keri* is the problem when the words are articulated.
Well, that's this opinion. רב חסדא Rav Chisda, אמר *Rav Chisda amar*,
next line, רב חסדא *Rav Chisda* says, הרהור hirhur לאו כדבור k'dibbur
דמי *hirhur lav kedibbur dami*. No, the first one was it is
כדבור *kedibbur*, it's just not a בעל קרי baal keri *ba'al keri*
problem. רב חסדא *Rav Chisda* says הרהור *hirhur* does not count as
speech and you're not יוצא yotzei *yotzei*. דסלקא דעתך הרהור כדבור דמי
hirhur k'dibbur dami *deisalka da'atach hirhur kedibbur dami*, if you think that
if you think it is like you said, so יוציא בשפתיו *yotzi
bisfatav*, you might as well say it. So he doesn't buy this
middle ground you can be יוצא yotzei, *yotzei* but it's not like
you said. If it's like you said, then you might as well
say it. אלא מאי *ella mai*? הרהור לאו כדבור דמי *hirhur lav
kedibbur dami*? So you're saying it's not like you spoke, which means
you're not יוצא yotzei *yotzei*. So למה מהרהר *lama meharher*? Why are
you thinking the שמע Shema *Shema*? You're telling me you're not יוצא
yotzei, *yotzei*. He's saying, he's saying, Rachel to answer you, I'm sorry,
I cannot have this guy be יוצא yotzei *yotzei* the שמע Shema
*Shema* without running into this problem about being a בעל קרי baal
keri, *ba'al keri* and therefore I'm sorry until he goes to the
מקוה *mikvah* or whatever. He is not going to be able to
say שמע Shema *Shema*. That's going to have to fall by the
wayside. But he could still think it. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says, what's the point of thinking it? So אמר רבי אלעזר *amar
Rabbi Elazar* כדי שלא יהא כל העולם עוסקים בו והוא יושב ובטל
*kedei shelo yehei kol haolam oskim bo vehu yoshev uvatel*. So everybody
else should not be saying שמע Shema, *Shema* and he is there
reading the newspaper, he is there not doing it. Because the שמע
Shema *Shema* is okay, but even at the same time, the שמע
Shema *Shema* is a declaration of קבלת עול מלכות ol malchus, שמים
*kabbalat ol malchut shamayim*, the גמרא'ס *Gemara's* going to emphasize it in
a minute, and therefore it is not something that you want to
sort of be seen as sort of stepping outside of even if
technically you're not יוצא yotzei *yotzei*, you want to be part of
that process of קבלת עול מלכות שמים malchus shamayim, *kabbalat ol malchut
shamayim* and you certainly don't want to be standing outside when everybody
else is doing it, which by the way why,
which is by the way why, which is by the way why
when if you're in the middle of doing something like let's say
פסוקי דזמרא *Psukei d'Zimra* and everybody else is up to שמע *Shema*,
you know, at the points where it's appropriate to interrupt, you're supposed
to say שמע *Shema* with them. Even though you're going to get
to שמע *Shema* in ten minutes or whatever, it should not be
that everybody is saying שמע *Shema* and you're not, right? So it's
so this is a basic declaration of faith. What does it mean
for you not to be doing this when everybody else is? So
yes, you're not יוצא *yotzei*, but that's important to be participating in
this way. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says וניגרס בפרקיה *venigras bepirkeih*,
a very sort of strange question. It sounds like you're just the
whole problem was just that you're reading the newspaper. But why does
it have to be שמע *Shema*, says the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, you
know, why not just look in a גמרא Gemara *Gemara* when people
are saying the שמע *Shema*? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says alright,
anyway, we'll work that out later. אמר רב אדא בר אהבה *amar
Rav Adda bar Ahava* בדבר שהציבור עוסקים בו *bedavar shehatzibur oskim bo*.
Okay. So we want you to be doing the same thing they're
doing, to not just to not be doing something, you know, not
related to תורה Torah *Torah*, we want you to be participating in
the same act. Okay, so that's why you're not יוצא *yotzei* and
if you think it it's not a problem of בעל קרי baal
keri *ba'al keri* because that's why the תלמוד תורה talmud Torah, *Talmud
Torah* answer, it's not a problem of בעל קרי baal keri *ba'al
keri* for not יוצא *yotzei* because because because it's not like you
spoke it, so it's not a problem about בעל קרי baal keri
*ba'al keri*, but it's also you're not יוצא *yotzei*. So the whole
point about thinking it is just to not be standing outside.
So women also בעל קרי
baal keri *ba'al keri*, correct, we will get to that. The whole
בעל קרי Ba'al Keri *ba'al keri*.
Women are not always in this position, you know, of the of
being there, the men are not
really counting but being there to participate, to show their
participation.
Not getting credit, but it's
an interesting perspective, yeah, I hear the point. Right, you're supposed to
you're supposed to participate although you're not really getting credit, alright, you're
not really, right, in the same way, yes.
I'm confused the difference between what רב הונא *Rav Huna* said and
what רב חסדא *Rav Chisda* said will come out whether we say
הרהור כדיבור דמי *hirhur kedibbur dami* or לאו כדיבור דמי *lav kedibbur
dami*.
Right. Yeah. The question is when you're thinking, are you יוצא *yotzei*
and or not? So one answer is you're יוצא *yotzei*, so then
why not just say it? Because you're יוצא שמע *yotzei Shema*, but
saying it creates problems with בעל קרי Ba'al Keri *ba'al keri*. Saying
the spoken word is a particular problem with this בעל קרי baal
keri *ba'al keri* and therefore even though you're יוצא *yotzei*, we don't
want you to say. And the other approach is because you're not
יוצא *yotzei* and and you can't say it to be יוצא *yotzei*
because then it is a בעל קרי baal keri *ba'al keri* problem.
And even though you're not יוצא *yotzei* you should still think it
in order so that you should be, you know, doing the same
thing everybody else is doing. So the difference is are you יוצא
*yotzei* the שמע *Shema*, yes.
I'm a little challenged by how the lack of modesty or privacy
around this kind of thing, because what might happen to you at
night in your house should not be public.
Yeah, so so who says this is public? This is not saying
that we're not saying that this is what? Who said this? This
is this is self-regulated. Nobody is nobody is the בעל קרי baal
keri, *ba'al keri* police here. This is self-regulated. I'm serious.
Nobody's going to notice if you're not saying שמע *Shema*.
Oh, you mean why so
maybe
you're
right, so maybe that's part of the answer of that you should
not be you shouldn't be standing outside the ציבור tzibbur *tzibur*, not
just the theological point, but maybe the point you're making as well.
But the bottom line is at the end of the day it's
not a problem. You're you're acting as if, you know, you're saying
people looking if your lips are moving? I don't think that's the
you know I that maybe that's actually what the point is about
thinking along as well is to address that issue about the public
aspect. Anyway, let's say we see what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says.
והרי תפילה tfilah. *ve'harei tefillah*, והרי תפילה tfilah. *ve'harei tefillah* בדבר שהציבור
עוסקים בו *bedavar shehatzibur oskim bo*. How about דאוונינג *davening*, right? The
משנה mishnah *Mishnah* did not mention what the story is about שמונה
עשרה Shmoneh Esrei, *Shmoneh Esrei*. That that's something that everybody's standing up
to דאוון *daven*, but it's not. היה עומד בתפילה ונזכר שהוא בעל
קרי baal keri *hayah omed bitefillah venizkar shehu ba'al keri*, you got
up to דאוון *daven* and you were in the middle of שמונה
עשרה Shemoneh Esrei *Shmoneh Esrei* and then you remembered that you were
בעל קרי *ba'al keri*. So לא יפסיק *lo yafsik*, don't interrupt your
דאוונינג *davening* once you're in the middle אלא יקצר *ela yekatzer*, do
a short version of it, but continue to דאוון *daven* שמונה עשרה
Shemoneh Esrei. *Shmoneh Esrei*...
אתה חונן *Atah Chonen*... I know.
טעמא דאתחיל *ta'ama de'atchil*. So the reason is... it's really hard to
talk over. The reason is is that you began. הא לא אתחיל
*ha lo atchil*, if you didn't begin לא יתחיל *lo yatchil*, you
shouldn't begin. So it's clear you don't stand up to דאוון *daven*.
So why do you silently participate in the שמע *Shema* and you
don't at least silently participate in the דאוונינג *davening*? Because presumably if
you don't begin means you don't do anything, you're sitting and they're
standing up and דאוונינג *davening*. Why shouldn't you also silently be participating
in the דאוונינג *davening*? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says שאני תפילה
tfilah דלית בה מלכות שמים d'leis bei malchus shamayim, *shani tefillah d'leit
bah malchut shamayim*. No, that's different. There's a... and this is getting
this I probably read this into the earlier גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, maybe
the earlier גמרא Gemara *Gemara* was more like Rachel just now, not
to be standing outside, but the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says it's not
just about not not doing what everybody is doing, it's about not
doing. Something that's about accepting God's, the yoke of heaven, something so
central as the שמע, not to be doing that when everybody else
is doing it. Something like שמנה עשרה Shmoneh Esrei is not as
big as a deal, you're sitting there doing שמנה עשרה, Shmoneh Esrei,
which then raises Rachel's problem to begin with, wonder why you're sitting.
But all right, but that's yours, that's fine.
So it says מלך העולם. melech ha'olam. I understand. Okay, so two
things. First of all, Rashi makes an interesting point, which is not
so much פשט pshat of the גמרא, Gemara and Rashi himself admits
it in some
ways, which is that the standard נוסח הברכה nusach habracha of אלוהינו
מלך העולם Eloheinu Melech Ha'olam
is not in any of the ברכות brachos of שמנה עשרה, Shmoneh
Esrei, right? All the ברכות brachos of שמנה עשרה Shmoneh Esrei are
ברוך אתה השם המלך הקדוש, Baruch Atah Hashem haMelech haKadosh, או האל
הקדוש, o haEl haKadosh, whatever it is. Anyway, המלך הקדוש, haMelech haKadosh,
anyway, so it doesn't have the מלך העולם. melech ha'olam. But the
more point is, it's not just a mentioning of God's מלכות. malchus.
It's the very fact of the act of שמע is the act
of the statement of עול מלכות, the statement of faith of accepting
upon yourself God's, you know, God's godship, God's kingdom, you know, the
obligation to love God, that is the central act of declaration of
faith. Okay, that's something we don't want somebody to not in some
way be participating with as opposed to תפילה. tfilah Okay, so that's
the גמרא's Gemara answer. So גמרא Gemara says ואימא, ve'eima, if that's
your issue that you only participate when silently, or however you're participating,
this בעל קרי because of מלכות שמים, malchus shamayim. what about בירכת
המזון birchas hamazon לאחריו? le'acharyav? What about the benching afterwards? דלית בה
מלכות שמים, malchus shamayim. there's no מלכות שמים. malchus shamayim, דתנן, ditnan,
על המזון מברך לאחריו, al hamazon mivarech le'acharyav, אינו מברך לפניו, eino
mivarech lefanav, that you do, he does the benching afterwards. So why
do you do the benching afterwards? It's not about מלכות שמים. malchus
shamayim So גמרא Gemara says fine, אלא קריאת שמע ובירכת המזון דאורייתא
ותפילה דרבנן. ela krias shema u'virchas hamazon d'oraisa u'tfilah d'rabanan. The basic
dividing line is, the בעל קרי does what's biblical, which is שמע
and benching, he doesn't do what is rabbinic, which is the which
is the תפילה. tfilah, Now, now, there's
first of all, there's another גירסא girsa here. There's another גירסא girsa
which is okay, קריאת שמע krias shema is מלכות שמים, malchus shamayim,
בירכת המזון birchas hamazon is biblical, and תפילה has neither. It's neither
מלכות שמים malchus shamayim nor biblical. The interesting part about that גירסא
girsa is that we'll see in a minute that some opinions, which
you'll be shocked based on everything we've seen until now, that שמע
is דרבנן, derabbanan, that although we say ובשכבך ובקומך, u'v'shochbecha u'v'kumecha, it's
really talking about learning תורה Torah and there's no biblical obligation of
שמע. There are going to be some opinions like that. So some
say even if that's true, שמע gets extra extra attention because of
מלכות שמים, malchus shamayim, even if it's only דרבנן, derabbanan, and בירכת
המזון birchas hamazon gets extra attention because it's biblical. But תפילה has
neither the biblical aspect or the מלכות שמים aspect and therefore if
you're a בעל קרי, you don't participate at all. Now, this is
the גמרא's answer. So at the end of the day, what are
the things a בעל קרי does? The things that are biblical, maybe
also מלכות שמים, what does he not do, the things that are
rabbinic. At the end though, the גמרא does not attend to, pay
attention to the issue about why is the שמע with just thinking
and the בירכת המזון birchas hamazon is articulated. That's not in the
גמרא. So that goes back to what I said. One answer is
that even when it says בירכת המזון birchas hamazon it's just thinking.
The other answer I gave was that maybe שמע you could be
יוצא when you're thinking, which is not true by בירכת המזון, birchas
hamazon, although this גמרא is now saying that according to רב חסדא,
you're not יוצא either. So if you're not יוצא either, right, what's
the difference? So I very much like what Dov said which is
maybe the other difference is is that saying the words of תורה,
Torah right,
is more of a problem than the words of בירכת המזון. birchas
hamazon. So maybe that also somewhat factors into the difference as well.
Yeah, well, that's a good point. Okay, but it's still a different
type of experience. Anyway, that is important that the גמרא does not
spell out, is more interested in what do you participate and not
participate and not why שמע is in your mind and the בירכת
המזון birchas hamazon is articulated. Okay, yes.
ותפילה דרבנן, utfilah derabbanan, what does the גמרא mean by that?
It means that they're certainly the there's a general debate in general
whether all prayer is דרבנן, derabbanan, but even the רמב״ם Rambam who
says that there's a daily מצוה mitzvah of prayer biblically, says it's
certainly not the certain text that we have. So there's no need
to directly participate in that no need, but the the sense that
you must that you must do this תפילה, this שמנה עשרה Shmoneh
Esrei is biblical,
is not true according to anybody. So therefore the demands for that
are much less.
Okay, why can't the בעל קרי daven? Yeah, and you know, a
lot of it is is our own needs. Why is that such
an, you know, why is that so inappropriate for him to be
doing? I'm sorry? The בעל קרי, like in other words he's really
not supposed to be דאווענינג, davening, right? Yeah. But why not?
In other words because it's about saying שם השם, shem Hashem, meaning
you're right, what exactly the בעל קרי is אסור assur in.
Like he eats something.
Okay, we'll see about No, he cannot make a ברכה. bracha. The
משנה mishna, says a בעל קרי is not מברך לפניו. mivarech lefanav.
No, no, מזונו, mezono, like he wants to eat something.
No, no, we will see that what a בעל קרי cannot do
is not just not say תורה, Torah which is, you know, which
is they saying the שמע, but basically he can't say שם השם.
shem Hashem. Okay, so we will get to that in the גמרא,
but that is right, the point that a בעל קרי basically. Now
I should mention by the way that this idea about the בעל
קרי actually, just pay attention, the idea about the בעל קרי actually
in some אשכנזי Ashkenazi communities in the Middle Ages similar types of
concerns were applied to women who were נדה. Niddah. Okay? That the
idea of being in a particular state which you cannot just not
say פסוקים and not read the שמע and so on, but here
you're not בענטשינג Benching or whatever you're, or you're not saying the
ברכות Brachos beforehand, you're not saying שמונה עשרה, Shemoneh Esrei, has a
lot just שם השם Shem Hashem becomes a problem. So we will
see that, we'll see it more explicated later, but that's certainly implicit
about all of this.
Right. Well, they never said it by women, it was just certain
מנהגים. Minhagim. All right, let's take a look. אמר רב יהודה. Amar
Rav Yehuda. All right, let's try to get a little further. אמר
רב יהודה. Amar Rav Yehuda. מנלן לברכת המזון לאחריה מן התורה? Menalan
le'Birkat HaMazon le'achareiha min HaTorah? I know, I know the דף Daf
is too interesting. מנלן לברכת המזון לאחריה מן התורה? Menalan le'Birkat HaMazon
le'achareiha min HaTorah? How do you know ברכת המזון Birkat HaMazon is
biblical? שנאמר, She'ne'emar, the פסוק Pasuk. says ואכלת ושבעת וברכת, V'achalta v'savata
u'veirachta,
that you eat and be satisfied and you bench and you give
a blessing. Now of course we mentioned it's on the ארץ Aretz
and maybe it's only ושבעת V'savata but at least anyway it's biblical.
מנלן לברכת התורה לפניה מן התורה? Menalan le'Birkat HaTorah lefaneha min HaTorah?
How do you know the ברכה Bracha of תורה Torah beforehand is
biblical? Some people probably didn't know that, that ברכת התורה Birkat HaTorah
is considered biblical. How do you know that? שנאמר She'ne'emar כי שם
השם אקרא הבו גודל לאלוהינו. Ki Shem Hashem ekra havu godel l'Eloheinu.
When I declare the name of God,
you shall give greatness to our to our God. So רש"י Rashi
says what that means is that משה Moshe is saying before I'm
about to teach you תורה, Torah the שירה, Shira, I will call
out in the name of God, I'll make a ברכת התורה Birkat
HaTorah and you all say אמן, Amen, הבו גודל לאלוהינו. Havu godel
l'Eloheinu. But I think more simply what the גמרא is saying is
when you are about to call out in the name of God,
אקרא, Ekra, particularly also the word קרא, Kra, the תורה Torah. read
like the קריאת שמע Kriat Shema and so on, God's name, then
the response to that should be הבו גודל, Havu godel, to bless
God's name and therefore by the way when we learn ברכת התורה
Birkat HaTorah we discussed that there are aspects of it which are
ברכת המצוה, Birkat HaMitzvah, but the idea that it's a ברכה Bracha
that's biblical to say ברכות התורה Birchot HaTorah is much more about
the שבח Shevach aspect of it, אשר בחר בנו מכל העמים ונתן
לנו את תורתו, Asher bachar banu mikol ha'amim v'natan lanu et Torato,
certainly the point that the רמב"ן Ramban makes. And therefore the idea
of when you're about to encounter תורה Torah to to thank God
and to bless God for the gift of the תורה, Torah, that
is seen as biblical learned from this פסוק.
Somewhere there's יהא שמיה רבא Y'hei Shmei Rabba is an alternative translation
of הבו גודל. Havu godel.
Oh, that's a good point, יישר כח. Yasher Koach. That's a great
point. Right. What?
Almost 40 point.
That's a very good point. Okay, רש"י Rashi, is going to get
to the יהא שמיה רבא Y'hei Shmei Rabba in a bit. אמר
רבי יוחנן: Amar Rabbi Yochanan: למדנו ברכת התורה לאחריה מברכת המזון וברכת
המזון לפניה מברכת התורה מקל וחומר. Lamadnu Birkat HaTorah le'achareiha mi'Birkat HaMazon
u'Birkat HaMazon lefaneha mi'Birkat HaTorah mi'kal va'chomer. We can figure out that
there's a biblical obligation to say blessings over the Torah afterwards, referring
presumably to the ברכות Brachos you make when you get an עליה
Aliyah from and that it's biblical based on ברכת המזון Birkat HaMazon
where there's a ברכה Bracha after and the reverse, ברכת המזון לפניה
מברכת התורה מקל וחומר. Birkat HaMazon lefaneha mi'Birkat HaTorah mi'kal va'chomer.
The idea of saying a ברכה Bracha before you eat food we
can learn out from saying a ברכה Bracha before you learn תורה
Torah, מקל וחומר. mi'kal va'chomer. How does it work? ברכת התורה לאחריה
מברכת המזון מקל וחומר. Birkat HaTorah le'achareiha mi'Birkat HaMazon mi'kal va'chomer. We
can learn out the blessing of the Torah afterwards from the benching
by the following way. ומה מזון שאין טעון לפניו טעון לאחריו. U'ma
Mazon she'ein ta'un lefanav ta'un l'acharayiv. By food where you don't have
to make a ברכה Bracha before, you nevertheless have to make biblically
you have to make a ברכה Bracha afterwards. תורה שטעונה לפניה. Torah
she'te'unah lefaneha. Torah where you do make a ברכה Bracha before, so
it's more demanding
than food because you make a ברכה Bracha before. אינו דין שטעונה
לאחריה? Eino din she'te'unah l'achareiha? How much more so should it be
at least like food that you make a ברכה Bracha afterwards? Then
you could reverse it. וברכת המזון לפניה מברכת התורה מקל וחומר. U'veirchat
HaMazon lefaneha mi'Birkat HaTorah mi'kal va'chomer. And then you could figure out
that you have to make a ברכה Bracha before food from Torah.
מקל וחומר. Mi'kal va'chomer. ומה תורה שאין טעונה לאחריה. U'ma Torah she'ein
te'unah l'achareiha.
Torah that you don't make after, you still make before, טעונה לפניה,
te'unah lefaneha, you make a ברכה Bracha before Torah. מזון שהוא טעון
לאחריו. Mazon she'hu ta'un l'acharayiv.
Food that you have to make a ברכה Bracha after, it should
at least be as it's more weighty than Torah that you make
a ברכה Bracha after. So it should at least be as weighty
as Torah that you make a ברכה Bracha before. אינו דין שטעון
לפניו? Eino din she'ta'un lefanav? How much more should you have to
make it before. Now you might be noticing that this is worse
than circular. Well it's worse than circular in the sense that once
you prove one point, the rest falls off. If you're going to
make the argument that, okay, based on this קל וחומר kal va'chomer
I'll say that you make ברכות התורה Birchot HaTorah after, well then
you can't make a קל וחומר kal va'chomer the other way to
get anything about benching because the whole קל וחומר kal va'chomer was
based on the asymmetry in both directions. If you're trying to create
symmetry you lose your קל וחומר. kal va'chomer. That's number one. Number
two is, as with all things, קל וחומר kal va'chomer is very
formalistic. It doesn't look at the substance of why are there these
differences. Maybe there's a particular reason why ברכת המזון Birkat HaMazon comes
after, ברכת התורה Birkat HaTorah comes before. So that point actually the
גמרא says in terms of the first question רש"י Rashi says, yes,
we're not saying there's no ברכה Bracha before, no ברכה Bracha after,
but what we're saying is the תורה Torah, is explicit by ברכת
המזון Birkat HaMazon after, and explicit by ברכת התורה Birkat HaTorah before,
that creates this imbalance that allows us to make a קל וחומר
kal va'chomer even if we're trying to say you make both, there
still is a difference that one the תורה Torah is explicit by.
תורה Torah emphasizes it here,
the other it emphasizes
it there.
Well, okay, כי שם ה׳ אקרא ki shem Hashem ekra explicit. No,
I mean, not explicit, I mean explicit through the rabbinic eyes. No,
not as explicit, that's not the word, but still through the rabbinic
interpretation, what it says is the תורה Torah still through the rabbinic
interpretation says by ברכת המזון Birkat HaMazon after and says by תורה
Torah, before, and that creates this asymmetry that lets us make a
קל וחומר kal vachomer even if at the end result we're trying
to say they're all the same. Anyway, now the גמרא turns to
the fact that substantively they're different. You can't just make a קל
וחומר. kal vachomer. The גמרא says like this: איכא למפרך, ika lemifrach,
you can challenge it, and you can say the following. מה למזון
שכן נהנה, ma lemazon sheken nehene, in one way ברכת המזון Birkat
HaMazon, is stricter and therefore has more demands because you actually derive
physical benefit. And therefore, if there's something demanded by ברכת המזון, Birkat
HaMazon you cannot assume it's demanded by ברכת התורה Birkat HaTorah because
ברכת המזון Birkat HaMazon. has a quality that ברכת התורה Birkat HaTorah
does not, that you actually derive physical benefit. ומה לתורה שכן חיי
עולם, u-ma la-Torah sheken chayei olam, and the reverse is true of
תורה. Torah, תורה Torah you don't get a physical benefit, but you
get עולם הבא. olam haba. So therefore it's a tremendous spiritual thing.
So there might be things that are demanded by ברכת התורה Birkat
HaTorah not demanded by ברכת המזון. Birkat HaMazon Now even at this
stage the גמרא is still making a formalistic distinction. Oh, you can't
make a קל וחומר, kal vachomer, this has a way it's more
strict and this has a way it's more strict in a different
way, so who knows you can't say anything. But these differences might
actually explain the substantive difference of why one is after and one
is before. Because if ברכת המזון Birkat HaMazon you derive benefit, the
most appropriate time to make a ברכה bracha is after you've experienced
that physical benefit. Then you feel most appreciative is when you've actually
experienced. You could argue, no, you feel most appreciative when you're hungry
and you're ready to eat the food, but there's a sense of
that it's in response to the benefit that you received and therefore
comes after you've received. In תורה, Torah you're not receiving the benefit
now or after you learn the תורה, you're receiving the
benefit עד מאה ועשרים. ad mea v'esrim. So therefore there's no idea
of waiting till after because that's not the idea of to have
actually experienced the benefit and it's really the fact that you're about
to involve yourself in the experience of תורה, that itself is enough
to heighten your sense of the appreciation and the time to be
making the ברכה. bracha. So the difference the גמרא says of before
and after is not just a technical difference, why you can't learn
one from the other, but it goes to the heart of why
one is before and why one is after. Let's just finish this.
The גמרא says like this: ותנן, ve-tenan, we taught in a משנה,
על המזון מברך לאחריו ואינו מברך לפניו, al hamazon mevarech leacharav ve-eino
mevarech lefanav, that a בעל קרי says the ברכת המזון Birkat HaMazon
and he doesn't say the ברכה bracha beforehand. So you see that
only the ברכת המזון Birkat HaMazon is biblical and not the ברכה
bracha beforehand. תיובתא, tiyuvta, that is a contradiction. So it's quite fascinating
the גמרא actually thought for a minute that the ברכת הנהנין, birkat
ha-nehenin, the ברכה bracha we make on bread beforehand is biblical, but
that is rejected. But what we do say is biblical is ברכת
המזון afterwards and ברכת התורה Birkat HaTorah beforehand. And so that's where
we'll stop now. The גמרא is obviously going to continue with these
questions about which parts of שמע are biblical or rabbinic. But before
we end for today, I did want to mention one thing because
we had mentioned the issue of הרהור כדבור דמי or not, that
there's a very important discussion in תוספות Tosafot about
somebody
who is in the middle of שמונה עשרה and
basically hears and the ציבור gets up to קדיש Kaddish or יהא
שמיה רבה. Yehei Shmei Rabba. What does he do? So רש"י says,
not here but another רש"י, he says you're silent and you're יוצא
because of שומע כעונה. shomea k'oneh. So תוספות Tosafot says, one minute,
if שומע כעונה shomea k'oneh then you're talking, you're interrupting your שמונה
עשרה. So תוספות actually suggests maybe you're not silent. In the end,
he agrees to רש"י and that similar to the point we made
here about the first position, that הרהור could be כדבור in the
sense that hearing or thinking is enough to be יוצא, but it
doesn't literally have the same weight of having said it. On the
one hand, not to have the problems of this בעל קרי saying
the words of תורה and directly encountering the words of תורה to
create that problem, and on the other hand, in the case of
in the middle of שמונה עשרה, not to be considered an interruption.
So there could be a way in which thinking counts but is
not actually considered as speech in a number of areas. And I
should actually just end by a final one final point which ties
in. There's a debate of the גר"א Gra and the שולחן ערוך
Shulchan Aruch about whether you make a ברכת התורה birkat ha-Torah when
you are thinking תורה or not. And part of that debate has
to be, like everybody says you're יוצא the מצוה mitzvah of תלמוד
תורה, talmud Torah. and if you're not יוצא, you mean you spend
an hour thinking about something in תורה, of course you're יוצא the
מצוה mitzvah of תלמוד תורה. talmud Torah But part of that debate
is exactly this question about whether the ברכת התורה birkat ha-Torah is
about the מצוה of תלמוד תורה and then you would do it
before you think תורה, or is it about, like we say כי
שם ה׳ אקרא, ki shem Hashem ekra, the encountering of the words
of תורה and that requires the giving of שבח shevach to God?
And therefore it's only when those words are enunciated that it creates
that type of demand of giving a ברכה. bracha. So the same
way those enunciation creates a challenge in terms of the בעל קרי,
it also creates this, it's the same issue of these words of
תורה that create this demand of giving the ברכת התורה. birkat ha-Torah.
So these issues about So we had originally spoken about the הלכה
halacha that someone who is a בעל קרי is not supposed to
be מברך mevarech and they have to think the
words instead.
The גמרא asks a question and says if you're thinking it's considered
like speaking then what's the difference? If you're thinking and it's like
speaking you're also מברך. mevarech. But if you say thinking is not
like speaking then you're not יוצא with your ברכה. bracha. Either way
it doesn't seem to make any sense. So the גמרא answers it's
interesting because the heart needs a purification but if you're just speaking
it doesn't need purification. It's a very strange גמרא but it's another
piece where we find that there's a difference between thinking something and
saying something. There's another famous passage in גמרא that deals with the
idea of thinking and saying something. A person who is an אנוס,
onus, let's say a person is being forced to make a certain
נדר neder or a certain vow, the person can say something and
think something else. If a person is saying one thing and thinking
another thing then maybe the words that he says don't really have
any meaning. So the גמרא says there's a concept of דברים שבלב
אינם דברים. devarim shebalev einam devarim. If you say something but you
think something else it's what you say that matters. We don't go
according to what you think. And yet there are exceptions to this
rule.